I've already released one episode on the
topic, but here we are again to go
through parts of a podcast by a glycine
expert being interviewed on the powerful
anti-inflammatory benefits of glycine.
But we're not here to passively listen.
We're here because this is the
centeruge.
Have you ever wondered what is real from
what is total BS or even half BS in
health podcasts? Well, wonder no more.
In this episode, I'll pop open the
studies and filter everything through a
scientific lens, and I'll cite my
sources. Like last week, the glycine
expert is Dr. Joel Brind, author of the
glycine miracle and a professor and a
PhD of biomed sciences, being
interviewed by Dr. Autumn Smith, a
holistic nutrition doctorate. In this
episode, we'll be covering a few things.
One, diabetes being an inflammatory
disease. Two, fat not causing diabetes.
The immune system does. Three, fat
cells. They don't multiply. They just
keep expanding. Four, C15 and cell
fragility syndrome. You'll really want
to stick around for this one because I
have some
we'll just say fun things to say. And
five, of course, glycine deficiency
causes inflammation.
Okay, let's wind up the centeruge.
>> Oh, yeah. And I'm going to tell I'm
going to give you a chance to really
I've tried sweet and I love it. We're
going to talk about it in a second.
There's two other things I am dying to
have you comment on. But first, I just
wanted to say too, there's this really
cool trial you highlight several times
in your book in 2008. Cruz I think was
the first.
>> And they supplemented with glycine.
Yeah. And um they saw a reversal
lowering of some inflammatory markers
and also I think improved insulin
sensitivity. But these people didn't
lose weight. And that's usually the
mantra is like you got to lose weight in
order to reverse diabetes. But why was
glycine able to change it despite weight
loss or what what is your theory around
that? I remember it being
>> well the theory is again that that that
uh diabetes is an inflammatory
condition.
>> Uh there are uh they they found that for
example
that the the the thing what has to do
with weight is and this was discovered a
couple of decades ago is that it's not
it's not so much fat atapost tissue it's
abdominal fat. It's that's the fat that
gets you. And what they found more
recently maybe 10 years ago is that it's
not even the fat that causes the
inflammation. It is the macrofasages
which are resident in the fat, those
first responders. And fat tissue is very
interesting. When you make fat, you know
when when tissue grows,
excuse me, what happens? Cells multiply.
That's how most tissue grows. Not fat
exactly. Fat grows. you put on fat, you
know, you get a depo of fat that maybe
is 5 pounds. Now it's 10, now it's 20.
If you go and you look at the cells, the
cells count is the same. Each individual
cell gets fat. All right, right into
claim one. Diabetes is an inflammatory
disease. So I tracked down the CRU
study. It's this one where people with
type two diabetes were given either a
placebo or an inert pill or glycine over
3 months. And then they looked at a few
blood measures of inflammation like a
receptor for a highly inflammatory
molecule called TNF alpha and another
immune molecule called interfuron. We
can see that all here. The black boxes
are the glycine conditions and the white
are the placebo. If the boxes go down,
that's less of the respective
inflammation marker. But we're more
interested in the comparison against
placebo because it accounts for what's
known as the placebo effect.
Essentially, your body may react to
something simply because you
psychologically know that you're taking
something new, even though you don't
know if you're consuming the inert
substance, the placebo or the glycine.
Anyway, for the first interlucan one
beta, a pro-inflammatory molecule,
there's no effect. Same for interlucan 6
below it, though both conditions seem to
experience reduction. Then the most
telling is this receptor of TNF alpha,
also pro-inflammatory. it seems to
reduce more with glycine. Now,
interestingly, interferon, a stimulator
of the immune system, seemed raised with
glycine compared to the placebo. Now, if
you're wondering what in the world is
going on here and how to translate
things going nowhere, some things are
going up, some things are going down
into useful information, then you, my
friend, are asking the right questions.
And you might expect a PhD like me to
tell you, "Oh, yes, there's an obvious
pattern of glycine being super cool and
super great, but I'm actually rowing the
same boat as you to a world of
confusion. Typically, these kinds of
data are pretty weak. That's all over
the place, and there's no consistency.
And then it's up to the researchers to
hypothesize what might be going on,
which usually they default to clearly
glycine is totally awesome. But the
reality is this is just telling us that
glycine has an effect. But it isn't
clear if that effect is good or bad. But
before you send me to the stockades and
stone me, I can ease your confusion by
mentioning that there are other studies
that gave glycine to different groups of
people and found more consistent
anti-inflammatory effects. So, it seems
likely that glycine is
anti-inflammatory. Still, this doesn't
prove that diabetes is an inflammatory
disease. It just speaks to this one
study that they briefly discussed. So,
Dr. Bry is half correct. The reason that
I say half is because yes, there's a
good amount of literature discussing
diabetes as an inflammatory disease. And
we can even prove that diabetes is an
inflammatory disease because in this
study, researchers gave people an
anti-inflammatory drug. I'm not talking
ibuprofen. I'm talking a big hitter.
Here, we're looking at glycated
hemoglobin. So, the A1C test that you
can order and tracks your long-term
measures of blood glucose. See how it is
reduced with the anti-inflammatory drug.
This is a randomized control trial. So,
this proves Dr. Brian's point. Diabetes
is an inflammatory disease. Except I did
say 50% or at least that's kind of a
best guess. And that's because raising
inflammation alone doesn't cause
diabetes. There has to be some metabolic
component too. meaning your liver,
muscle, pancreas also have to be
stubbornly not cooperating. We know that
can occur due to genetics, but it
commonly occurs from consuming too much
food over longer periods of time that
ultimately taxs our pancreas, leading to
a slow creeping up of insulin and blood
glucose. Now, it's difficult to
completely separate the immune from the
metabolic considering that they're so
tightly intertwined. But when we have
insulin, a largely metabolic hormone in
this context to diabetics, they
experience improvements like here. Now,
both groups are given insulin, but the
intensive treatment is given more along
with more monitoring of metabolic
measures like blood glucose. We're
looking at that long-term marker again,
HBA1C. The lower the lines go, the
better. So, clearly managing metabolic
aspects of health also led to
significant improvements. Now, I'll
repeat, to really untangle these two
would take a lot more research that we
actually have, but would suck up the
rest of the time of this video. They're
tightly related. Still, overall, we can
say that diabetes is a complex disease,
including mixture of metabolic and
inflammatory causes. And yes, glycine is
anti-inflammatory. Now, something in
line with that thought process is the
idea, the claim that your fat mass
doesn't cause diabetes. It's actually
the immune cells that do. And Dr. Brian
has a point which I've covered in
content before where more visceral fat
leads to stronger immune reactions,
meaning more of the quote unquote bad
body fat around your organs typically
increases a pro-inflammatory state in
the body. However, in those studies,
they do show that it's the fat cells
themselves that secrete the molecules
that influence nearby immune cells. So
could easily claim that the impact still
begins at the fat cell itself. But we
can do tests of this more directly using
animal studies and we can't do this in
humans FYI by simply looking at mice
that are immunompromised. So these mice
have no immune system or at the very
least a significantly dampened one. And
then researchers feed them a crap diet
and guess what happens?
They develop diabetes. Now, a
counterargument could be that the immune
cells knocked out are not the same type
as the ones hanging out smoking cigars
and drinking whiskey with the fat cells,
if they do that or not, is unconfirmed.
That would be a fair argument, but I
still think that this is at least
nudging towards the idea that insulin
resistance being caused by inflammation
initially is unlikely. The main point,
fat cells, especially visceral fat
cells, are likely the greater
contributor to diabetes as they are the
start point of a lot of inflammation
that comes with chronic disease.
And as an additional quick claim thrown
out there that I thought I'd cover, Dr.
Brian mentions that fat cells don't
multiply, they only expand. Now, fun
fact, that has a bit more interesting
nuance to it. It's true that fat cells
have an amazing ability to take up fat
molecules which grow the single fat cell
itself. However, the body also replaces
fat cells, meaning that we do have the
ability to generate more fat cells,
though the absolute number even with
this turnover is somewhat constant.
Anyway, an interesting side note. Now,
let's get into something that I'm quite
passionate about. C15 and cellular
fragility. So creates more and more fat
within each cell. And what happens then
is that the cells become more fragile.
In fact, there's there's even a
particular kind of fat that you find in
whole milk and butter and meat and so on
that you don't find in any of the
vegetarian sources that people are also
deficient in. That makes the cells more
fragile.
>> C15.
>> Yes. What's that?
>> Did you say C-15?
>> Yes. C15, right?
>> Paninoic acid. Yep.
>> Yeah. Pentadoninoic acid. That was
Stephanie Ben uh
>> Watson. Ben Jackson. Ben Jackson.
>> Ben Watson, I think.
>> Ben Watson or one of the Yes, that's
right. Working for the uh she worked
with porpuses. Sounds like a fascinating
job to have. But anyway, she um so she
discovered this uh pentadoninoic acid
which is again has to do with cellular
fragility. So I think um it's glycine
deficiency. It's also
the uh pentadoninoic acid deficiency.
uh and if you and I don't take
pentidoric acid uh supplements because
you know I I I eat you know whole whole
foods and meats and you know lots of fat
and milk fat and you know butter fat and
all that. So, uh, I shouldn't shouldn't
be really deficient in that. But what
I'm saying is that in as you get fatter
and when you get obese, not only does
the amount of fat increase in each cell
in in the abdominal fat basically, but
because those cells are more fragile and
they get damaged very easily, uh, you
have more and more macrofasages
generating more and more inflammation
because of glycine deficiency. So the
claim here is that C-15, a 15carbons
saturated fat molecule deficiency leads
to something called cellular fragility.
Now this term cellular fragility was
coined by a researcher named Dr.
Stephanie Ven Watson. And I have several
videos analyzing multiple studies on
C-15 fats. But to give you a short
version, cellular fragility syndrome
coined here is the idea that our cells
and their cell membranes essentially the
skin and the bones of the cell are
stabilized and made stronger by the
inclusion of C-15 fats in the membrane.
Okay. Well, what if I told you that
there is a study that tested this? And
what if I told you that the review that
I just cited written exclusively by Dr.
for Vin Watson failed to include said
study. And what if I told you that the
study which applied C-15 directly to the
cells did not detect an iota of
difference in the membrane stability
from this increase in C-15? Well, you
might begin to feel as strongly as I do
that buying C-15 fat supplements for 50
bucks a month or whatever it is now may
just do nothing for cellular fragility
syndrome. And beyond that, you might
actually start thinking that cellular
fragility syndrome is nonsense, which is
exactly what I think. Anyway, this
paired with the clinical data and
multiple other studies that I've covered
in the past, I'll link my videos for
you, lead me to strongly disagree with
any notion that our cells are deficient
in C15 and that they need more C-15 to
be healthy. Trust me, there's a lot more
I could say here, and I probably will
release another video dissecting the
studies on cell fragility syndrome in a
dedicated video, but for now, I'll leave
you with that small taste. Bottom line
is, forget the C-15 and cell fragility
syndrome. Save your money. I strongly
disagree with Dr. Bryant here. Okay, but
none of that means that Dr. Bryan's
comments on glycine and inflammation are
wrong, though. His final claim is that
glycine deficiency causes inflammation.
Before we touch on that, if you're
looking for a deeper dive, I have an
extended version of this video that
includes much more on inflammation like
the inflammosome,
a deeper dive into C-15 and cell
stability, and more on several of the
studies that I briefly went over here.
If you're interested, no pressure. You
can access all of my videos, a catalog
of hundreds, full analyses, which are ad
free, plus come with articles for each
video and one paragraph highlight
summaries. And you get access to my
private podcast that releases every
month, live sessions with me, my master
supplement guide, and much more. I put a
lot of work into it. It's called the
Physionic Insiders. Again, if
interested, then click the link to join
the insiders in the description box.
Well, there's a few ways to assess this,
like associative studies that do show
that as blood levels of glycine are
lower, people tend to have more
inflammatory markers. That would go in
line with Dr. Brian's perspective. But
he's more specific than that. He says
macrofasages, a particular type of
immune cell becomes more inflammatory
when glycine is not present. Now we can
test that directly by simply applying
glycine to macrofasages and seeing if
they become less inflammatory. And
that's also been done. And again, Dr.
Bryant is right. In basic terms, when
macrofasages, these immune cells are
exposed to an inflammatory agent called
LPS, the pro-inflammatory molecule
called TNF alpha, shoots up because the
macrofasages start producing it. But in
the condition right next to it, if
glycine is added, bam, significant
reduction. This is only one of several
studies showing that effect. So yes,
glycine is likely anti-inflammatory,
especially if we include randomized
control trials using glycine as a
supplement that we discussed earlier.
But there's something bothering me.
Here's the thing. The claim is that
glycine deficiency is leading to more
and more inflammation. And the problem
with that is that it's worded as an
absolute as in glycine is the key to
inflammation. We clearly see that it has
a relationship to inflammation and
glycine tends to suppress inflammation.
But in the absolute way of talking about
glycine, we end up ignoring everything
else as if it's inconsequential. And
that's a problematic framing in my mind.
And it's extremely easy to prove because
we can look at studies that do the exact
same thing but use other molecules like
I don't know vitamin C or vitamin D or
any number of different molecules that
are a completely independent of glycine
and b are given to macrofasages not
exposed to much supplemental glycine. So
they would be assumed to be likely
deficient in glycine. For example, this
study on curcumin or this study using
vitamin D. Both studies measured the
exact same inflammatory markers and more
and showed reductions. So if glycine
deficiency is the reason for
inflammation, then we can only resolve
inflammation through glycine, well this
would be impossible. The reality is
multiple things can be true without
hyperbole. Yes, deficiency in blood
glycine can associate with greater
inflammation. Yes, glycine
supplementation can reduce inflammation.
Yes, other molecules completely
unrelated to glycine can also reduce
inflammation even in a low glycine
scenario. So, in the end, the takeaway
is this. Glycine can be an
anti-inflammatory and important, but it
is unlikely to be the only player in
inflammation. So, we shouldn't overindex
on glycine alone. Okay. Again, I realize
that was a lot. So, like leftovers at
your friend's house, what can you take
home with you? Dr. Brind gets several
things correct and several things
incorrect. That's the neutral take based
on the evidence. Now, in terms of what
the evidence suggests, one, diabetes
probably isn't solely an inflammatory
disease. Inflammation may be part, but
it's not the whole. Two, high body fat,
while it may work through immune cells
and raising inflammation, is still the
major reason for diabetes, especially if
it's visceral fat. Three, fat cells,
fascinatingly tend to expand more than
they renew or multiply. Four, save your
money on C-15 fats. They're sold under
multiple arguments, but one of the
common ones is cell fragility syndrome,
which is provably weak at least. And
finally, five, glycine is an
anti-inflammatory shown across many
studies. However, it probably isn't the
only thing to be focused on, and there's
obvious big players like being over fat,
smoking, alcohol, and the like. And then
there's many other molecules that also
have potent anti-inflammatory effects.
So, overindexing on glycine alone is not
warranted, even if it does seem to be a
helpful supplement. But you may want to
know more about C-15. In which case,
check out my dedicated analysis right
here. Or if you prefer to centrifuge
another podcast with me as your nerdy
host, let's get into another one right
here. Thanks a ton for tuning in and I
hope you learned something useful today.
Talk to you in the next one. Bye.